Kimberly A. Dill-McFarland, PhD

Bioinformatics Research Consultant University of Washington Box 358061, Division of Allergy and Infectious Diseases 1-206-595-1828; kadm@uw.edu; in 💟 💆 kdillmcfarland

Microbiology PhD with 7+ years experience in microbiome research and data science education. Expertise in next-generation sequencing including library generation, data processing, and statistical analysis. Effective communicator to both expert and novice audiences with experience teaching one-on-one and in large courses. Specific skills include:

General

- Multi-omic sequencing (Illumina, 454)
- Reproducible research (Github, Rmd)
- Multi-disciplinary collaboration •
- Diverse communication strategies

Computational

- Unix/Linux
- R/RStudio
- Python
- Git
- mothur, QIIME
- AWS, Google Cloud

Statistical

- Uni- and multivariate linear models
- Dimensionality reduction (PCA, nMDS)
 - Co-variance and correlation
- Sparse dataframes

EXPERIENCE

07/2019 - present

Bioinformatics research consultant, Division of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, U. of Washington

Complete data cleaning, quality assessment, and statistical analyses for various projects with Drs. Hawn and Altman

08/2017 - 06/2019

Post-doctoral research fellow, Microbiology & Immunology, U. of British Columbia

- Directed Experiential Data Science for Undergraduate Cross-disciplinary Education (EDUCE) including a team of 3 teaching assistants
- Designed and implemented data science curriculum in R/RStudio, command line tools, and cloud resources in 7 undergraduate courses
- Secured independent funding for EDUCE (\$160K+)

07/2018 - 06/2019 Post-doctoral research fellow, ECOSCOPE

- Coordinated data science workshops for Ecosystem Services, Commercialization Platforms, and Entrepreneurship (ECOSCOPE)
- Refined online content and acted as primary webmaster

07/2016 - 06/2017 Post-doctoral research associate, Bacteriology/Sociology, U. of Wisconsin-Madison

- Investigated the relationship between the human gut microbiome and long-term behaviors using the Wisconsin Longitudinal Study (WLS)
- Applied multiple regression analyses with confounder and multiple comparison correction in R
- Navigated large, longitudinal survey databases using R and Git

08/2011 - 06/2016 Graduate research assistant, Bacteriology, U. of Wisconsin-Madison

- Thesis: Assessing the impact of diet on microbial succession, growth, and milk production in dairy cows
- Designed and implemented amplicon sequence analysis pipelines in mothur and R on both local and remote resources
- Collaborated effectively with diverse international researchers resulting in numerous publications as first, middle, or corresponding author
- Mentored high school, undergraduate, and graduate students

08/2008 - 05/2011

Undergraduate research assistant, Biology, U. of Puget Sound

- Thesis: Investigating maltose metabolism in Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus
- Acquired independent funding through the American Society for Microbiology (\$10K)

EDUCATION

2011-2016	Ph.D. Microbiology, U. of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, WI. GPA: 4.00
2007-2011	B.S. Molecular and cellular biology , Minor mathematics, U. of Puget Sound, Tacoma, WA, GPA: 3.84

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

*co-first authors For full publication list

Dill-McFarland KA*, Tang Z*, Kemis JH, Kerby RL, Chen G, Palloni A, Sorenson T, Rey FE[†], Herd P[†]. 2019. Close social relationships correlate with human gut microbiota composition. <u>Sci</u> Rep 9: 703. doi: 10.1038/s41598-018-37298-9

Dill-McFarland KA, Weimer PJ, Breaker JD, Suen G. 2018. Diet influences early microbiota development in dairy calves without long-term impacts on milk production. <u>Appl Environ Microbiol</u> 85(2): e02141-18. doi: 10.1128/AEM.02141-18

Vogt NM, Kerby RL, **Dill-McFarland KA**, Harding SJ, Merluzzi AP, Johnson SC, Carlsson CM, Asthana S, Zetterberg H, Blennow K, Bendlina BB[†], Rey FE[†]. 2017. Gut microbiome alterations in Alzheimer's disease. Sci Rep 7(1): 13537. doi: 10.1038/s41598-017-13601-y

NOTABLE ACCOMPLISHMENTS

2017, 2018, 2019	Session moderator/convener at the American Society for Microbiology (ASM) Microbe meeting
2016	Microbiome Digest's Best Microbiome Paper
2016	Sigrid Leirmo Memorial Award for peer mentorship and support
2009, 2010	American Society for Microbiology Undergraduate Fellow

Full Curriculum vitae

References available upon request